Preliminary Guide to the Collection of Early Graphic Art
Yale University Arts Library
Collection of early graphic art
1528-1836
AOB 74
Yale University Arts Library
0.5
(2 boxes)
This collection contains examples of graphic art, primarily before 1800. Many of these materials are not dated; an educated guess as to the age of the material was based on paper type and subject matter.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Collection of Early Graphic Art was housed in the former Arts of the Book Collection until its transfer to the Robert B. Haas Family Arts Library in 2008.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains examples of graphic art, primarily before 1800. Many of these materials are not dated; an educated guess as to the age of the material was based on paper type and subject matter.
Arrangement
Organized into five series: I. Figurative. II. Typography. III. Landscape & Architecture. IV. Nature. V. Ornamentation.
Broadsides -- Specimens; Prints; Graphic arts; Broadsides
- Figurative, Series I
  Scope and Contents
  This series includes a variety of figurative works.
  - Groups, several with explanatory text., 1624-1747 undated; 12 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Portraits or single figures, one hand-colored., 1557-1795 undated; of 29 items, 16 in envelope (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Groups: historical, biblical, and genre scenes., 1578-1797 undated; 9 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Typography, Series II
  This series includes works with typographical elements.
  - Book pages, calendars., 1623-1836 undated; of 60 items, 3 in envelope, 33 pages "Bills of Lading" in smaller folder (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Didactic posters, plates and book pages, engraving specimens, one hand-colored., 1528 undated; of 31 items, 23 in small folder (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Standes-Listes., 1798 1807; 2 (Folder 1)
- Landscape & Architecture, Series III
  This series includes scenes of life in and around buildings, depictions of architectural ornament, and one seascape.
  - Includes architectural ornament (doors, sculpture) and estate plans., 1688 undated; 21 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Mantels, etc., 1787 undated; 11 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Mantels, altars, and landscapes proper., undated; of 23 items, 7 in envelope (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - A military scene, a plan of Westminster, university buildings, a tomb., 1616 1720 1792 undated; 4 (Folder 1)
- Nature, Series IV
  This series includes mostly renderings of animals.
  - Depictions of nature., undated; 11 items (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Prints of fish, insects, and other animals, many hand-colored., 1734 undated; 29 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Ornamentation, Series V
  This series includes examples of miscellaneous ornamentation.
  - Depictions of ornamentation., 1690 1705 undated; of 32 items, 22 in envelope (Box 2, Folder 11)